# Chirag Gupta, Ph.D.

Postdoctoral Associate Waisman Center, University of Wisconsin Madison, Wisconsin, USA Webpage: cngupta.github.io Email: cngupta@protonmail.com





## SUMMARY

Computational biologist with 4+ years of postdoctoral experience in research and analysis of multi-modal genomics data. Specifically, my research straddles between **regulatory genomics**, **network biology**, and **machine learning** with an aim to develop computationally tractable models of human diseases. I am currently working on projects focused on strategies to guide disease **biomarker discovery**, **drug repurposing**, and **patient stratification** using **multi-modal single-cell** genomic data of the **human brain**. I have extensive experience in written and oral communication to academics and business leaders through contributions to winning grants, 12+ peer reviewed publications, and several conference appearances.

## **EDUCATION**

| EDUCATIO |   |                                |
|----------|---|--------------------------------|
| 2017     | Ph.D. Computational Biology                         |                                |
|          | (Cell and Molecular Biology)                        | University of Arkansas,        |
|          | Dissertation: Transcriptome-based gene networks for | Fayetteville, Arkansas, USA    |
|          | systems-level analysis of gene function             |                                |
| 2009     | M.Sc. Bioinformatics                                |                                |
| 2007     | B.Sc. Bioinformatics                                | Sardar Patel University, India |
|          |   |                                |

## RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

| <ul> <li>PsychENCODE2, PsychAD</li> <li>Single-cell genomics of the human brain</li> <li>Network medicine</li> <li>2017 – 2020</li> <li>Postdoctoral Research Associate</li> </ul> |    |
|--|----|
| Network medicine   |    |
|  |    |
| 2017 – 2020 Postdoctoral Research Associate  |    |
|  |    |
| <ul> <li>Plant and crop genomics</li> </ul>  |    |
| <ul> <li>ML for gene prioritization in networks</li> </ul>   |    |
| <ul> <li>Web-applications for network analysis</li> <li>University of Arkansas,</li> </ul>   |    |
| 2012 – 2017 Graduate Research Assistant Fayetteville, Arkansas, USA  |    |
| <ul> <li>Plant stress and developmental biology</li> </ul>   |    |
| <ul> <li>Large-scale transcriptomics</li> </ul>  |    |
| <ul> <li>Gene regulatory networks</li> </ul>   |    |
| 2008 — 2009 Student Researcher Disha Life Sciences Pvt. Ltd  | ٠, |
| <ul> <li>Insilico analysis of fusion proteins in Gujarat, India</li> </ul>   |    |
| cancer   |    |
| <ul> <li>Protein structure prediction</li> </ul>   |    |
| <ul> <li>Molecular modeling, drug designing</li> </ul>   |    |

## **PUBLICATIONS**

Under review/preprints

- 1. Yheni Dwiningsih, Julie Thomas, Anuj Kumar, **Chirag Gupta**, Navdeep Gill, Charles Ruiz, Jawaher Alkahtani, Niranjan Baisakh, Andy Pereira. Identification of QTLs and Candidate Loci Associated with Drought-Related Traits of the K/Z RIL Rice Population. (*preprint*)
- 2. **Chirag Gupta**, Arjun Krishnan, Andrew Schneider, Cynthia Denbow, Eva Collakova, Pawel Wolinski, Andy Pereira. SANe: The Seed Active Network for Discovering Transcriptional Regulatory Programs of Seed Development. (*preprint*)

## Peer reviewed journal articles

- Chirag Gupta, Jielin Xu, Ting Jin, Saniya Khullar, Xiaoyu Liu, Sayali Alatkar, Feixiong Cheng, Daifeng Wang. Single-cell network biology characterizes cell type gene regulation for drug repurposing and phenotype prediction in Alzheimer's disease. *Plos Computational Biology*, *July 2022*. [full text] [cover story]
- Chirag Gupta, Pramod Chandrashekar, Chenfeng He, Ting Jin, Saniya Khullar, Qiang Chang, Daifeng Wang. Bringing machine learning to research on intellectual and developmental disabilities: taking inspiration from neurological diseases. *Journal of Neurodevelopmental Disorders* (IDDRC 2022 special issue on computational neuroscience), *May 2022.* [full text]
- 3. Anuj Kumar, **Chirag Gupta**, Julie Thomas, Andy Pereira. Genetic Dissection of Grain Yield Component Traits Under High Nighttime Temperature Stress in a Rice Diversity Panel. **Frontiers in Plant Science**, September 2021. [full text]
- 4. **Chirag Gupta**, Venkategowda Ramegowda, Supratim Basu, Andy Pereira. Using network-based machine learning to predict transcription factors involved in drought stress resistance. *Frontiers in Genetics*, *June 2021.* [full text]
- 5. Raksha Singh, Rohana Liyanage, **Chirag Gupta**, Jackson Lay Jr., Andy Pereira, Clemencia Rojas. The protein interactomes of AtNHR2A and AtNHR2B unraveled common and specialized functions in plant immunity integrating distinct biological processes. *Frontiers in Plant Science*, *March 2020.* [full text]
- 6. Min Woo Lee, Carmen S. Padilla, **Chirag Gupta**, Aravind Galla, Andy Pereira, Jiamei Li, Fiona L. Goggin. The FATTY ACID DESATURASE 2 family in tomato contributes to primary metabolism and stress responses. *Plant Physiology*, *Nov. 2019.* [full text]
- 7. **Chirag Gupta** and Andy Pereira. Recent advances in gene function prediction using context-specific coexpression networks in plants. *F1000Research*, Feb. 2019. [full text]
- 8. Arjun Krishnan, **Chirag Gupta**, Madana MR Ambavaram, Andy Pereira. RECoN: Rice Environment Co-expression Network for systems level analysis of abiotic-stress response. *Frontiers in Plant Science*, Sep. 2017. [full text]
- 9. Venkategowda Ramegowda, Upinder Singh Gill, Palaiyur Nanjappan Sivalingam, Aarti Gupta, **Chirag Gupta**, Geetha Govind, Karaba N Nataraja, Andy Pereira, Makarla

Udayakumar, Kirankumar S Mysore, Muthappa Senthil-Kumar. GBF3 transcription factor imparts drought tolerance in Arabidopsis thaliana. *Scientific Reports*, *August 2017.* [full text]

 Venkategowda Ramegowda, Supratim Basu, Chirag Gupta, Andy Pereira. Regulation of grain yield in rice under well-watered and drought stress conditions by GUDK. Plant Signaling and Behavior, January 2015. [full text]

## **CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS**

Select talks

- Single-cell network biology characterizes cell type gene regulation for drug repurposing and phenotype prediction in Alzheimer's disease. Alzheimer's Association International Conference, San Diego, CA, 2<sup>nd</sup> August 2022
- Predicting rice genes important for drought tolerance using gene regulatory networks and machine learning. Crops InSilico, 4th Annual Symposium and Hackathon, Urbana, IL, 3<sup>rd</sup> May 2019
- Arabidopsis seed-filling association-network analysis. American Society of Plant Biologists – Southern Section (ASPB-SS), Lexington, KY, 30<sup>th</sup> March 2014.

# Select posters

- Single-cell network biology characterizes cell type gene regulation for drug repurposing and phenotype prediction in Alzheimer's disease, Intelligent Systems for Molecular Biology, Madison, WI, July 2022
- Network analysis of human brain cell types under Alzheimer's disease and healthy conditions, Society of Neuroscience, Chicago, IL, November 2021
- Network-based approach to prioritize lung cancer genes from whole-exome sequencing data. Arkansas Bioinformatics Consortium, Little Rock, AR, 25th March 2018
- [Award winning poster] An abiotic-stress conditioned gene regulatory network in rice
  predicted using an ensemble of reverse-engineering solutions. The 25th Plant and Animal
  Genome (PAG) Conference, San Diego, CA, 14th January 2017
- A resource for systems analysis of stress response in rice. NSF Workshop on plant development and drought stress, Monterey, CA, 8th November 2015
- In Silico Analysis of Fusion Proteins in Cancer, International Conference on Biomedical and Genomic Research, Ahmedabad, India, 30th January 2009

#### AWARDS

- Crops in silico underrepresented minority travel scholarship, Crops InSilico, Urbana, IL, 2019
- 2. Scherago International Student Travel Grants Awards, **The 25th annual Plant and Animal Genome (PAG) meeting**, San Diego, CA, 2017
- 3. NSF Travel Grant to attend the Workshop on Plant Development and Drought Stress, **National Science Foundation**, 2015
- 4. Stood 3rd in merit list for all India entrance examination for Master's in bioinformatics program, **Sardar Patel University**, India, 2007
- 5. 2nd Prize in undergraduate oral presentation, Sardar Patel University, India, 2006
- 6. 3rd Prize in undergraduate poster competition, Atmiya University, India, 2006

## **GRANT CONTRIBUTIONS**

- NSF EPSCoR RII Track-2 FEC 1826836: Systems genetics studies on rice genomes for analysis of grain yield and quality under heat stress (PI: Dr. Andy Pereira; \$4,659,406), 2018
- **NSF MCB 1716844**: Systems genetics analysis of photosynthetic carbon metabolism in rice (PI: Dr. Andy Pereira; \$798,725.00), 2017

## **SOCIETY MEMBERSHIPS**

2019 - present

2022 - present

The International Society for Computational Biology (ISCB)

The Alzheimer's Association International Society to Advance

Alzheimer's Research and Treatment (ISTAART)

## SELECT SKILLS

Programming R, Python, Perl

Bioinformatics Extensive knowledge and experience with sequence data (NGS) processing

pipelines (single-cell, bulk); quality control, variant calling, differential gene

expression, gene-set enrichment analysis, network analysis

Data science Machine learning (data cleaning, feature extraction, model training and

evaluation); multi-modal data integration and analysis

Visualization R, Shiny, Cytoscape

Platforms Docker; Linux, MacOS; Google Cloud

## Tools Developed

GRAiN http://rrn.uark.edu/shiny/apps/GRAiN/
SANe https://plantstress-pereira.uark.edu/SANe/
RECoN https://plantstress-pereira.uark.edu/RECoN/

#### MENTORING EXEPRIENCE

Mentored a graduate student (Masters in Statistics, UW) and four undergraduate students under the University of Madison's Undergraduate Research Scholar contract for two semesters, 2021-2022. Project title: "Using network-based machine Learning to predict genes underlying neurological disorders"

#### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Co-taught Plant Genomics (**Bioinformatics/Genomics modules**: CSES 5543, Uni. Of Arkansas), 2016, 2018

## **EXTENSION ACTIVITIES**

Student and Teacher Workshop: rice genetic variation (18 credit hours, Uni. Of Arkansas), 2019

## **ACADEMIC SERVICE**

• External reviewer for IEEE International Conference on Bioinformatics and Biomedicine (BIBM) 2022.

- Specialty review editor for Frontiers in Bioinformatics and Frontiers in Genetics
- **Manuscript reviewer** for Human Molecular Genetics, Journal of Neurodevelopmental Disorders, Plant Physiology, Frontiers in Plant Science, Nature Scientific Reports, Rice, Plant Cell Reports, Horticultural Plant Journal, Plant Methods, PLoS One, iMETA.
- Plante Fellow 2019: Contribution to the Plantae online portal for Bioinformatics resources relevant to plant biology research
- **Member of the panel of judges** for the Northwest Arkansas Regional Science and Engineering Fair 2015,16
- Conducted several training material and hands-on activities for undergraduates and K-12 students from the Arkansas agricultural areas in the Delta region for a STEM literacy outreach program

# **R**EFREES

Available upon request